Guide to the Peter E. Palmquist Photographs
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Peter E. Palmquist photographs
1950-2003
WA Photos 524
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
44.3
(109 boxes) + 7 broadsides.
Photographic material that chiefly documents Peter Palmquist's professional life as a photographer. This includes images from his service in the United States Army, mainly with the Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe in Paris, France, 1955-1959, as well as his career as a staff photographer for Humboldt State University, Arcata, California, 1961-1989. The latter photographs include significant documentation of the Theater Arts Department and its productions. Other photographs and negatives document his freelance, fine art, and wedding photography. A large group of copy photographs in the collection document Palmquist's research interests on a range of subjects with a focus on photography, especially its role in the history of the American West, particularly in California.
Palmquist, Peter E.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Peter Palmquist and the Estate of Peter Palmquist on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana and Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2003-2004.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
The Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University, has several collections assembled by Peter Palmquist.
The personal papers of Peter Palmquist are included in the Peter Palmquist Papers (WA MSS S-2965). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University
Biographical information and photographic materials related to women photographers are included in the Peter Palmquist Collection of Women in Photography (WA MSS S-2600). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Biographical information and photographic materials related to male photographers active in the western United States are included in the Peter E. Palmquist Collection of Male Photographers in the American West (WA MSS S-2733). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Biographical information and photographic materials related to male photographers active in Humboldt County, California, are included in the Peter Palmquist Collection of Humboldt County, California, Male Photographers (WA MSS S-2670). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Cased photographs are included in the Peter Palmquist Cased Photographs Collection (WA Photos 402). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Unique and rare photographic formats collected by Palmquist are in the Peter E. Palmquist Collection of Photography and Photographic Formats (WA Photos 490). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Stereograph cards that depict California are included in the Peter E. Palmquist Collection of Stereographs of California (WA Photos 494). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Books and periodicals formerly in the personal library of Peter Palmquist are accessible via the library catalog by searching for: "Palmquist, Peter E., Ownership."
Peter E. Palmquist (1936-2003)
A photographer, collector, and historian of photography, Peter Eric Palmquist was born in Oakland, California on September 23, 1936. In 1944, he moved with his family to Ferndale, California, and he spent most of his life in Humboldt County. During adolescence, Palmquist trained himself in photography. He served in the United States Army as a photographer from 1955 to 1959, mainly with the Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe in Paris, France. Palmquist worked briefly as a photographer for the state government of California from 1959 to 1961. From 1961 until his retirement in 1989, Palmquist worked as a staff photographer for Humboldt State University, Arcata, California, where he also graduated with a Bachelor of Arts degree in Art in 1965.
From 1971 until his death, Palmquist collected textual materials and hundreds of thousands of photographic items documenting the practice and occupation of photography from its beginning through the turn of the twenty-first century. He had particular interest in early California photographers, photographers of the American West, and women photographers.
A self-trained researcher and historian of photography, Palmquist organized more than one hundred exhibitions and wrote more than three hundred articles and a hundred monographs. He was a founding editor of The Daguerreian Annual, and a president of the National Stereoscopic Association.
Palmquist died January 13, 2003, in Oakland.
Scope and Contents
Photographic material that chiefly documents Peter Palmquist's professional life as a photographer. This includes images from his service in the United States Army, mainly with the Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe in Paris, France, 1955-1959; his personal travels through Europe during his military service including Belgium, England, Gibraltar, Italy, Malta, Netherlands, and Switzerland; his career as a staff photographer for Humboldt State University, Arcata, California, 1961-1989 including significant documentation of the Theater Arts Department and its productions; images that document significant events in Humboldt County, California from 1961 to circa 1990 including the Christmas flood of 1964; and thousands of black and white and color negatives that document weddings in Humboldt County from 1960 to roughly 1990. Other photographs and negatives document his freelance and fine art photography. Large groups of copy photographs document his research interests on a range of subjects with a focus on photography, especially its role in the history of the American West, particularly in California.
Arrangement
Organized into eleven series: I. United States Army Photographs, 1952-1959. II. Personal Photographs During Military Service, 1955-1959. III. General Photographs, 1960-2002. IV. Wedding Photographs, 1960-circa 1990. V. Humboldt State University, 1962-1972. VI. Christmas Flood of 1964, 1964. VII. Logging Road in the Jackson Demonstration State Forest, 1967. VIII. Nudes, circa 1973. IX. Copy Photographs, undated. X. Peter Palmquist Retrospective, circa 1950-2002. XI. Oversize Photographs, 1957-1995.
Cities and towns -- California -- Pictorial works; Floods -- California -- Humboldt County -- Pictorial works; Photographers -- History; Photographers -- California; Photographers -- West (U.S.); Photography -- History; Photography -- California; Photography -- West (U.S.); Photography, Artistic; Tourism -- Europe; Weddings -- Pictorial works; Wedding photography -- California -- Humboldt County; Belgium -- Pictorial works; California -- Pictorial works; England -- Pictorial works; Gibraltar -- Pictorial works; Humboldt County (Calif.); Humboldt County (Calif.) -- Social life and customs -- 1961-2003; Humboldt County (Calif.) -- Pictorial works; Italy -- Pictorial works; Malta -- Pictorial works; Netherlands -- Pictorial works; Paris (France) -- Pictorial works; Switzerland -- Pictorial works; West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Negatives (photographs); Photographic prints; Transparencies; Palmquist, Peter E.; California State University, Humboldt -- Pictorial works; Humboldt State College -- Pictorial works; Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe -- Pictorial works; United States. Army ( Photographers)
- United States Army Photographs, 1952-1959; Series I; 0.83 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized chronologically with Palmquist's service in the United States Army, including images created by the Pictorial Section of Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe (SHAPE) that range before his tenure.
  Scope and Contents
  Photographs chiefly created by Palmquist and colleagues during his service in the United States Army as a photographer from 1955 to 1959, chiefly with the Pictorial Section of Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe (SHAPE) in Paris, France.
  - Photographic training at Fort Monmouth, New Jersey, and Fort Ord, California, 1955 February-May; 2 (Box 1)
  - Photographs at Camp Roberts, California, 1955 June-July; 3 (Box 1)
  - Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe
    - Photographs with captions and dates, 1952-1959 (Box 1)
      Photographic prints with typescript captions and dates on their versos for events related to Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe.
    - Portraits
      - Eisenhower, Dwight (Box 2)
      - Johnson, Leon W (Box 2)
      - Montgomery, Bernard (Box 2)
        Includes 3 color transparencies.
      - Norstad, Lauris (Box 2)
      - Unidentified, 3 (Box 2)
    - Pictorial Section
      Formal and informal portraits of members of the Pictorial Section of Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe, 1955-1959.
      - De Vries, Hendrik (Box 2)
      - Goedert, Dwane E. (Box 2)
      - Lee, Schubert (Box 2)
      - Moller, Donald H. (Box 2)
      - Wilson, John, Jr. (Box 2)
      - Unidentified personnel (Box 2)
      - Personnel, off-duty (Box 2)
    - Subjects
      - Aircraft (Box 2)
      - Buildings and structures (Box 2)
      - Cityscapes (Box 2)
      - Military personnel (Box 2)
      - Military personnel, winter exercises (Box 2)
      - Military personnel, women (Box 2)
      - Paris, France (Box 2)
      - Ships (Box 2)
      - Soviet Union (Box 2)
      - Tanks (Box 2)
- Personal Photographs During Military Service, 1955-1959; Series II; 3.9 linear feet (8 boxes)
  Series II is organized into four subseries: Negatives, Negatives and Photographic Prints, Photographic Prints, Color Transparencies.
  Non-military related photographs chiefly of sites in Europe created by Palmquist during his service in the United States Army as a photographer from 1955 to 1959.
  - Negatives, 1956 July-1959 August; 182 negatives (Box 3)
    Single frames of 120-millimeter black-and-white film negatives of sites throughout Europe. Images include sites in Belgium, including the Expo 58, also known as the Brussels World's Fair; England, including London; Gibraltar; Italy, including Rome and Sicily; Malta; Netherlands, and Switzerland, including Gornergrat and Zermatt. Several images include his friend Schubert Lee.
  - Negatives and Photographic Prints
    - Paris, France, Binder, 1955-1959; circa 1000 negatives (Box 4)
      Three-ring binder with 35 millimeter black-and-white film negatives and contact prints. Also includes a group of negatives in slide mounts.
    - Dated Material
      35 millimeter and 120 millimeter black-and-white film negatives and contact prints.
      - New York City, 1955 April (Box 5)
      - Rome, Italy, 1956 July (Box 5)
      - Portugal, 1956 September (Box 5)
      - Morocco, 1956 November; 3 (Box 5)
      - Spain, 1956 November (Box 5)
      - Paris, France, 1956 November (Box 5)
      - Spain, 1957 September; 2 (Box 5)
      - Switzerland, 1959 January (Box 5)
      - Switzerland and Spain, 1959 January, July (Box 5)
      - Malta, 1959 February (Box 5)
      - Portrait of Yves Klein, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Undated Material
      - France (Box 5)
        - Paris, 10 (Box 5)
          120 millimeter black-and-white film negatives and contact prints.
        - The Louvre, 11 (Box 5)
          4 by 5 inches black-and-white film negatives, contact prints, and photographic prints.
  - Photographic Prints
    Photographic prints, chiefly black-and-white except where noted.
    - England (Box 6)
    - France
      - Paris
        - Arc de Triomphe de l'Étoile (Box 6)
        - Cafés (Box 6)
        - Churches (Box 6)
        - Eiffel Tower (Box 6)
        - The Louvre (Box 6)
        - Markets (Box 6)
        - Montmartre (Box 6)
        - Nightlife (Box 6)
        - Notre-Dame de Paris (Box 6)
        - Paris Métro (Box 6)
        - Parks (Box 6)
        - People (Box 6)
        - Seine (Box 6)
        - Street artists (Box 6)
        - Street scenes, 2 (Box 6)
        - Unbound portfolio of photographs (Box 6)
        - Color photographs (Box 6)
    - Italy
      - Airport and aerial view (Box 6)
      - Boats (Box 6)
      - Buildings (Box 6)
      - People (Box 6)
      - Street scenes (Box 6)
    - Malta
      - Boats (Box 6)
      - Buildings (Box 6)
      - Landscapes (Box 6)
      - People (Box 6)
      - Street scenes (Box 6)
      - Printed ephemera (Box 6)
    - Morocco
      - Tangiers
        - Buildings (Box 6)
        - People (Box 6)
        - Street Scenes (Box 6)
    - Portugal
      - Boats (Box 6)
      - Buildings (Box 6)
      - Landscapes (Box 6)
      - People (Box 6)
      - Street scenes (Box 6)
    - Spain
      - Buildings (Box 6)
      - Bullfighting (Box 6)
      - Landscapes (Box 6)
      - People (Box 6)
      - Running of the bulls (Box 6)
      - Street scenes (Box 6)
    - Switzerland
      - L'Abbaye, 2 (Box 6)
      - Zermatt (Box 6)
      - Unidentified locations in Switzerland
        - Skiing (Box 6)
        - Street scenes (Box 6)
    - Unidentified locations
      - Children (Box 6)
      - Interiors (Box 6)
      - Landscapes (Box 6)
      - Orchestra (Box 6)
      - Street scenes (Box 6)
    - Oversize photographs
      Photographic prints larger than 8.5 by 14 inches and smaller than 14 by 18 inches.
      - Belgium 58 (Box 7)
      - Malta (Box 7)
      - Morocco (Box 7)
      - Paris, France (Box 7)
      - Portugal (Box 7)
      - Spain (Box 7)
      - Switzerland (Box 7)
      - Unidentified locations
        - Animals (Box 8)
        - Architectural details (Box 8)
        - Boating (Box 8)
        - Cityscapes (Box 8)
        - Flea markets (Box 8)
        - Fishing (Box 8)
        - Interiors (Box 8)
        - Portraits, children (Box 8)
        - Portraits, men (Box 8)
        - Portraits, women (Box 8)
        - Seascapes (Box 8)
        - Street artists (Box 8)
        - Street scenes, 3 (Box 8)
        - Structures (Box 8)
  - Slides and Color Transparencies
    - Slides of France, chiefly Paris, as well as Spain and Switzerland, circa 650 slides, 35 millimeters (Box 9)
      Slides housed in six boxes within one large box.
    - Andorra (Box 10)
    - Artwork by Yves Klein (Box 10)
    - Germany (Box 10)
    - Malta (Box 10)
    - Pamplona, Spain, 1957-1958 (Box 10)
    - Paris, France (Box 10)
    - Street scenes (Box 10)
    - Switzerland (Box 10)
- General Photographs, 1960-2002; Series III; 10.3 linear feet (26 boxes)
  Series II is organized into five subseries: Negatives and Photographic Prints in Envelopes, Negatives and Photographic Prints not in Envelopes, Photographic Prints by Subject, Black-and-white Transparencies, and Color Slides and Transparencies
  General photographic files of Palmquist related to his career as a photographer.
  - Negatives and Photographic Prints in Envelopes, circa 10,000 negatives
    Arranged chronologically followed by undated material.
    Negatives and strips of contact prints, as well as some photographic prints, derived chiefly from black-and-white negatives with dimensions of 35 millimeters, as well as some 120 millimeters and 4 by 5 inches, created by Palmquist and housed in his original envelopes, 1960-2002. The envelopes include a brief descriptive title for the images and the date. This component also includes a group of negatives and prints found interspersed in the other portions of the collection.
    Significant events documented in the images include the dedication of the Avenue of the Giants scenic highway in July 1960; the Century 21 Exposition in Seattle, Washington, in June 1962; Christmas Flood of 1964; and the dedication of the Lady Bird Johnson Grove in Redwood National Park on August 27, 1969. General topics include images of events at Humboldt State College (later Humboldt State University), fairs, logging, and sporting events, as well as landscape and cityscapes of sites throughout northwestern California. Images also include photographs of Palmquist's immediate and extended family, as well as friends.
    - 1960-1961, 54 envelopes (Box 11)
    - 1962, 45 envelopes (Box 12)
    - 1963, 47 envelopes (Box 13)
    - 1964, 33 envelopes (Box 14)
    - 1964-1965, 43 envelopes (Box 15)
    - 1966-1971, 45 envelopes (Box 16)
    - 1972-1973, 51 envelopes (Box 17)
    - 1973-1975, 54 envelopes (Box 18)
    - 1976-1979. 1983-1988, 107 envelopes (Box 19)
    - Undated, circa 1960-1988; 42 envelopes (Box 20)
    - Undated, circa 1973-1979; 47 envelopes (Box 21)
    - Undated, circa 1973-2002; 12 (Box 22)
  - Negatives and Photographic Prints not in Envelopes
    Arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Arcata, California (Box 23)
    - Bridge, possibly in France (Box 23)
    - Exhibits
      - Emma B. Freeman: With Nature's Children, Grace Hudson Museum, Ukiah, California, 1987 (Box 23)
      - Louise E. Halsey: An American Pictorialist, Humboldt State University, Arcata, California, 1985 (Box 23)
      - Return to El Dorado: A Century of California Stereographs from the Collection of Peter Palmquist, California Museum of Photography, Riverside, California, 1986 (Box 23)
      - Seely Studio: The Tradition Continues, Humboldt State University, Arcata, California, 1984 (Box 23)
    - Fishermen (Box 23)
    - Home (Box 23)
    - Home of Melvin A Schular in Bayside, California, 1971 (Box 24)
    - Humboldt County, redwood forests, and seascapes (Box 25)
    - Humboldt County scenes (Box 23)
    - Informal portraits, circa 2002 (Box 23)
    - Klamath River, California, salmon runs, 1963-1964 (Box 23)
    - Landscapes, 2 (Box 23)
    - Loggers (Box 23)
    - Metal springs (Box 23)
    - Portraits in turn-of-the-twentieth century clothing
      Group of black-and-white negatives with dimensions of 120 millimeters and 4 by 5 inches that depict children, women, and men wearing turn-of-the-twentieth century clothing, probably created by Palmquist at a fair or social event, circa 1975.
      - 120 millimeter negatives, circa 1975; circa 70 negatives (Box 26)
      - 4 by 5 inches negatives, circa 1975; circa 100 negatives (Box 27)
    - Self-Portraits of Peter Palmquist, circa 1975-1976; 2 (Box 23)
    - Photography studio (Box 23)
    - Portfolio (Box 23)
    - Redwood forest at Bull Creek, California, 1968 February 20 (Box 23)
    - Rotary arm speed testing device (Box 23)
    - Salmon bake, 1969 May (Box 23)
    - Shasta Dam on the Sacramento River, California (Box 23)
    - Seascapes, 2 (Box 23)
  - Photographic Prints by Subject
    Photographs chiefly created by Palmquist, but some may have been collected by him.
    - Advertising, EnviroTex (Box 28)
    - Aerial views (Box 28)
    - Agriculture (Box 28)
    - Animals (Box 28)
    - Arcata, California (Box 28)
    - Arcata Jubilee, logging contests (Box 28)
    - Basketball (Box 28)
    - Boats and fishing (Box 28)
    - Caribou Lake, California (Box 28)
    - Carson Mansion, Eureka, California (Box 28)
    - Century 21 Exposition, Seattle, Washington (Box 28)
    - Children (Box 28)
    - Children and parents (Box 28)
    - Cityscapes (Box 28)
    - Exteriors, details (Box 28)
    - Fairs (Box 28)
    - Fire (Box 28)
    - Forestry (Box 28)
    - Forests (Box 28)
    - Fort Ross, California (Box 28)
    - Humboldt County Commission on Human Rights, circa 1965 (Box 28)
    - Johnson, Claudia "Lady Bird," at the dedication of the Lady Bird Johnson Grove in Redwood National Park, 1969 August 27 (Box 28)
    - Klamath River salmon run (Box 28)
    - Landscapes (Box 28)
    - Logging, 2 (Box 29)
    - Mining (Box 29)
    - Mountain towns in California (Box 29)
    - Musée français de la photographie, Bièvres, France, circa 1984 (Box 29)
    - Night photography (Box 29)
    - Painting, probably by Helen Dora Lemprière in 1955 (Box 29)
    - Photographs on tombstones (Box 29)
    - Photography studio (Box 29)
    - Pioneer, California (Box 29)
    - Portraits, men (Box 29)
    - Portraits, women (Box 29)
    - Pottery by Jolyon Hofsted (Box 29)
    - Seascapes (Box 29)
    - Shasta State Historic Park, California (Box 29)
    - Still lifes (Box 29)
    - Theater (Box 29)
    - Oversize
      Photographic prints larger than 8.5 by 14 inches and smaller than 14 by 18 inches. This component also includes mock-ups for publications and advertising.
      - Advertising for an exhibition, Toad Hill-Other Nonsense & Jennifer, photographs by Peter Palmquist and illustrations by Janice Mae, 1974? February (Box 30)
      - Advertising, EnviroTex (Box 30)
      - Arcata, California, storefronts on the Plaza (Box 30)
      - Arcata Jubilee, 2 (Box 30)
      - Cityscape, urban detail, Tokyo, Japan, 2002 June (Box 30)
      - Copy photograph of a group of men by water, circa 1885 (Box 30)
      - Exteriors, details (Box 30)
      - Fairs (Box 30)
      - Ferndale, California, aerial photograph (Box 30)
      - Forests, 2 (Box 30)
      - Industrial, 2 (Box 30)
      - Klamath River, California, salmon run fishing (Box 30)
      - Landscapes (Box 30)
      - Logging show, mock-up (Box 30)
      - Motorboat races, possibly at Lake Tahoe (Box 30)
      - Motorcycle racing (Box 30)
      - Mountain towns in California (Box 30)
      - Night photography (Box 30)
      - Nudes (Box 30)
      - Playgrounds (Box 31)
      - Portfolio, mock-up (Box 31)
      - Portraits, children (Box 31)
      - Portraits, men (Box 31)
      - Portraits, women (Box 31)
      - Seascapes (Box 31)
      - Timber industry (Box 31)
      - Wedding portraits (Box 31)
  - Black-and-white Transparencies
    Black-and-white transparencies, positive and negative, copies of original photographs by Palmquist, which create versions of the images with high-contrast.
    - Child (Box 32)
    - Exterior details, 4 (Box 32)
    - Fishermen (Box 32)
    - Houses (Box 32)
    - Landscape (Box 32)
    - Portraits of women, 3 (Box 32)
    - Silverware (Box 32)
  - Color Slides and Transparencies
    Organized under two headings: Original Photographs and Copy Photographs
    Color slides, mounted and unmounted, as well as transparencies with original images by Palmquist. This component also includes copy photographs of his work. Images include his photographic work for Humboldt State University, as well as his personal art, documentary, and family photographs.
    - Original Photographs
      - Abstracts (Box 33)
      - Agriculture and farming (Box 33)
      - Arcata Jubilee (Box 33)
      - Automobile travel (Box 33)
      - Benicia, California (Box 33)
      - California missions (Box 33)
      - Canada, 1962 (Box 33)
      - Century 21 Exposition, 1962 (Box 33)
      - Christmas flood of 1964 (Box 33)
      - Exhibition, Return to El Dorado: A Century of California Stereographs from the Collection of Peter Palmquist, California Museum of Photography, Riverside, California, 1986 (Box 33)
      - Family portraits (Box 33)
      - Fishing (Box 33)
      - Forests and flowers (Box 33)
      - Fort Ross, California, 1974; 2 (Box 34)
      - Humboldt County scenes (Box 34)
      - Johnson, Claudia "Lady Bird," at the dedication of the Lady Bird Johnson Grove in Redwood National Park (Box 34)
      - Landscapes (Box 34)
      - Logging (Box 34)
      - Men with snakes (Box 34)
      - Metal smelting (Box 34)
      - Military (Box 34)
      - Monterey State Historic Park (Box 34)
      - Nudes (Box 34)
      - Nursing (Box 34)
      - Paintings, probably by Helen Dora Lemprière (Box 34)
      - Paintings (Box 34)
      - Paris, France, street scenes (Box 34)
      - Potter (Box 34)
      - Pottery (Box 34)
      - Pottery by Palmquist (Box 34)
      - Rappelling (Box 35)
      - San Francisco, California (Box 35)
      - Seascapes (Box 35)
      - Self-documentation (Box 35)
        Chiefly copy photographs created and compiled by Palmquist of his publications.
      - Sierra Nevada region, California (Box 35)
      - Sonoma County, California (Box 35)
      - Sutter's Fort Historical Monument, Sacramento, California (Box 35)
      - Trinity Alps, California (Box 35)
    - Copy Photographs